Inventory of the William John Fellner Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Writings by others, 1951-1984
  - Foss, Murray, "Some Corporate Practices Under Inflation and Disinflation," outline for Contemporary Economic Problems paper, 1982 (Box 61)
  - Fowler, Henry, undated (Box 54)
  - Frenkel, Jacob, "Exchange Rates, Prices and Money: Lessons from the 1920s", 1980 (Box 39)
  - Friedman Benjamin M.
    - "Monetary Policy for the 1976 Recovery", 1975 (Box 29)
    - "Public Disclosure and Domestic Monetary Policy," preliminary draft, 1976 (Box 56)
    - "The Relative Stability of Money and Credit 'Velocities' in the United States", 1980-1981 (Box 28, 39)
  - Friedman, Milton, "Monetary Policy and Economic Conditions," memorandum to the President's Economic Policy Advisory Board, 1983 (Box 60)
  - Giersch and Wolter, "Ausbruch aus der Stagnation", 1982 (Box 6)
  - Godley, Wynne and Adrian Wood, "Stock Appreciation and the Crisis of British Industry", 1974 (Box 2)
  - Gordon, Roger
    - "Assessing the Risk of Corporate Bankruptcies in the Recent Recession," prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38)
    - "Beyond Monetarism", 1982 December (Box 1)
    - "Discussion of Charles Schultz's 'Some Macro Foundations of Micro Theory'", 1981 (Box 10)
    - "Has the Inflation of the 1970s Been a Surprise?", 1977 (Box 10)
    - "The Output Cost of Disinflation in Traditional and Vector-Autoregressive Models," with Stephen R. King, prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38)
  - Graetz, Michael, "Description of Proposed Research on Taxation of Consumption, 1976 (Box 35)
  - Gramlich, Edward M.
    - "Evaluating Countercyclical Revenue Sharing", 1977 (Box 59)
    - "The Optimal Timing of Employment in a Recession", 1975 (Box 67)
    - "Responses to Price Shocks in Different Models of the Inflation Process", 1978 (Box 41)
  - Haberler, Gottfried
    - "The International Monetary System and the State of the World Economy", circa 1982 (Box 49)
    - "The Problem of Stagflation," AEI Project on Major Economic Problems, 1976 (Box 11, 38)
    - "Stagflation: An Analysis of its Causes and Cures," contribution to Fellner Festschrift, 1975 (Box 59)
  - Hall, R.E., "Investment, Interest Rates and the Effects of Stabilization Policies", 1977 (Box 3)
  - Hamburger, Michael "Targets and Indicators of Monetary Policy: A Comment", 1982 (Box 5)
  - Hendershott, Patric, "The Impact of a Tax Cut on Interest Rates and Investment, Crowding Out, Pulling In and All That," Conference on Tax Research, Treasury Department, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Hsiao, James, "A Pedagogical Note on Transformation Curve", 1974 (Box 64)
  - Hughes, John S., "Corporate International Diversification and Market Assigned Measures of Risk and Diversification", 1975 (Box 31)
  - International Monetary Fund, 1973-1974 (Box 39)
  - Jahr, Walter Adolf, "Inflation and Indexing", 1967 May (Box 5)
  - Jaszi, George, "Some Comments on the Economic Outlook and on Inflation", circa 1975 (Box 58)
  - Johannes, James M. and Robert H. Rasche
    - "Can the Reserves Approach to Monetary Control Really Work?", 1981 (Box 14)
    - "Money Multiplier Forecasts," prepared for Shadow Open Market Committee (Box 34)
  - Johnson, D. Gale, "Progress of Economic Reform in the People's Republic of China", 1982 (Box 49)
  - Johnson, Harry
    - "The Monetary Approach to Balance of Payments Theory", 1971 (Box 12)
    - "World Inflation and the International Monetary System", 1975 (Box 58)
  - Johnson, Keith, "Policy Choices in the Current Economic Situation", 1975 (Box 5)
  - Joint Economic Committee of the US, "US Economic Growth from 1976 to 1986" (Box 2)
  - Jones, Sidney, "The Capital Budget Alternative: Toward a Reconstruction of Federal Budgeting", 1982 December (Box 1)
  - Kafka, Alexandre, "The Future of Gold", undated (Box 59)
  - Kaldor, Nicholas, "The Role of Devaluation in the Adjustment of Balance of Payments Deficits", 1982 (Box 61)
  - Kalman, R.E.
    - "Identification from Real Data", 1982 (Box 3)
    - "System-Theoretic Critique of Dynamic Economic Models", 1979 (Box 34)
  - Katz, Smauel I., introductory remarks at German-American Forum, 1980 (Box 28)
  - Kendrick, John W.
    - "Comments on Paper by Edwin Mansfield, 'Long Waves and Technological Innovation'", 1982 (Box 60)
    - "Productivity and Economic Progress", 1956 (Box 36)
    - "Sources of Productivity Growth," draft, 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Total Investment and Productivity Developments", 1977 (Box 2)
  - Klopstock, Fred, "Recycling Petro-Dollars", 1974 (Box 39)
  - Kohn, Meir, "A Loanable Funds Theory of Unemployment and Monetary Disequilibrium", 1981 (Box 39)
  - Kosters, Marvin
    - Testimony, 1978 (Box 41)
    - "The Voluntary Wage and Price Standards: Reporting on Their Performance", 1980 (Box 39)
    - "Wage-Price Behavior, Prospects and Policies," draft, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Lawrence, Robert
    - "An Analysis of the 1977 Trade Deficit" (Box 10)
    - "Is Trade Deindustrializing America?", 1983 (Box 62)
    - "Toward a Better Understanding of Trade Balance Trends," prepared for Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1978 (Box 58)
  - Leeuw, Frank de, "An Alternative to Potential GNP and the High Employment Budget" and "A New Noncyclical Budget," draft, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Leeuw, Frank de and Thomas M. Holloway, "Measuring and Analyzing the Cyclically Adjusted Budget", 1983 (Box 25)
  - Leijonhufvud, Axel, "The Wicksell Connection", 1978 (Box 41)
  - Levin, Jay, "A Framework for Analyzing the Coordination of Stabilization Policies Between the US and the Rest of the World", undated (Box 66)
  - Levy, Frank, "Have Black Men Gained in Employment?" prepared for Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1980 (Box 60)
  - Levy, Michael, "Constraining Inflation: Concerns, Complacencies, and Evidence", 1975 (Box 35)
  - Lindsey, David E., "Recent Monetary Developments and Controversies," prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38)
  - Lluch, Constantino
    - "International Patterns in the Elasticity of the Marginal Utility of Income and Expenditure," with R. Williams, 1974 (Box 59)
    - "Questions and Answers About the Revision of the Composite Index of Leading Indicators", 1975 (Box 59)
  - MacCrimmon, Kenneth and Stig Larsson, "Utility Theory: Axioms versus Paradoxes", 1979 (Box 31)
  - Makin, John H., "Deficits and Interest Rates", 1982 (Box 30)
  - Martin, Preston, "Remarks Before the Society of American Business and Economic Writers", 1983 (Box 30)
  - Mayer, Helmut (Box 18)
  - McCulloch, J. Huston, "The Ban on Indexed Bonds, 1933-1977", circa 1978 (Box 34)
  - McLure, Charles E., "Integrating the Income Taxes: Sardines or Worms?", 1975 (Box 1)
  - McMahon, Christopher, paper for Brookings Institute conference on the European monetary system, 1979 (Box 11)
    Includes comments of Fellner
  - Meigs, A. James, "The Role of Information Disclosure in International Monetary Policy," prepared for American Enterprise Institute, 1978 (Box 56)
  - Meiselman, Daniel
    - "Business Conditions and Financial Markets", 1983 (Box 55)
    - Comment on Joseph T. Salerno's "Gold Standards: True and False," Cato Institute Conference, 1983 (Box 55)
  - Meltzer, Allan
    - "Central Bank Policy", circa 1980 (Box 54)
    - "Long and Short Term Interest Rates in a Risky World," with Angleo Mascaro, 1982 (Box 50)
    - "Monetarist, Keynesian and Quantity Theories", 1977 (Box 16)
    - "Monetary Reform in an Uncertain Environment," prepared for the 1982 meeting of the Mont Pèlerin Society (Box 14, 50)
    - "On Keynes and Monetarism," prepared for the Keynes Centenary, 1983 (Box 50)
    - "Velocity of the Money Base" (Box 2)
  - Menezes,Tressler, Kuhlman, "A Limited Joint Profit Maximization Theory of Collusion", undated (Box 4)
  - Mentre de Loye, Paul, "The European Monetary System: An Outlook", 1979 (Box 11)
  - Miller, Merton and Charles Upton, "Leasing, Buying and the Cost of Capital Services," Conference on Tax Research, Treasury Department, 1975 (Box 3, 31)
  - Mishkin, Frederick, "Why Should Consumer Sentiment Be so Important to Consumer Durable Expenditure?", 1977 (Box 10)
  - Mitchell, Daniel, "Recent Union Contract Concessions," prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38, 50)
  - Mitchell, Edward, testimony before Ways and Means Committee, 1975 (Box 59)
  - Modigliani and Steindel, "Is a Tax Rebate an Effective Tool for Stabilization Policy", 1977 (Box 3)
  - Molsberger, Josef, "How Floating Has Worked: A European View", undated (Box 61)
  - Moore, Geoffrey
    - "Another 1929?", undated (Box 37)
    - "Employment, Unemployment and the Inflation-Recession Dilemma", undated (Box 38)
    - "Employment vs. Unemployment as a Guide to Full Employment", 1975 (Box 64)
    - "Inflation and Statistics -- Again", 1981 (Box 14)
    - "A Long-Run Look at the Business Cycle", 1980 (Box 67)
  - Morgan, David R., "Inflation and Progressive Personal Taxation", 1975 (Box 64)
  - Murphy, J. Carter, "The United States in World Markets", 1977 (Box 36)
  - Murphy, Neil, "Bank Supervision and Regulation in the Sunshine", undated (Box 56)
  - Narasimham, Gorti, "Policy Multipliers in the BEA Quarterly Econometric Model," Survey of Current Business, undated (Box 37)
  - Nordhaus, William, "The Interaction between Oil and the Economy in the Industrialized Countries", 1980 (Box 5)
  - Novak, Michael, chapter from The Spirit of Democratic Capitalism, 1980 (Box 42)
    Includes memorandum from John Cooper
  - Office of Economic Research, "Economic Indicators", 1977 (Box 2)
  - Office of the Secretary of the Treasury, Office of Tax Analysis, "The Effects of Excise Taxes on Income Tax Collections", undated (Box 59)
  - Olsen, Leif, "The Bretton Woods Nostalgia," speech before the International Banking and Global Financing Conference, 1983 (Box 62)
  - Okun, Arthur
    - "Asset Markets," chapter 5, circa 1979 (Box 61)
      Includes memorandum to Wednesday Afternoon Club
    - "Inflation: Its Mechanics and Welfare Costs," Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1975 (Box 31)
    - Prices and Quantities: A Macroeconomic Analysis, 1981 (Box 42)
    - "Prices and Quantities in Cyclical Fluctuations", 1979 (Box 61)
    - "Statement by Arthur Okun, Brookings Institution, before Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs", 1978 (Box 5)
  - Olsen, Mancur, "Political Economy of Comparative Growth Rates", 1978 (Box 5)
  - Ott, Attiat, "Disinflation and the Federal Budget", 1983 (Box 3)
  - Peacock, Alan, "Reducing Government Expenditure Growth: A British View, Conference: Reassessing the Role of Government in the Mixed Economy", 1982 (Box 6, 14)
  - Penner, Rudolph
    - "Government Budgets", 1979 (Box 21)
    - "The Growth in Government Spending", undated (Box 36)
  - Perlman, Mark
    - "Collective Bargaining and Industrial Relations: The Past, the Present and the Future", 1983 (Box 3)
    - "Fertility in Social Science Models", 1977 (Box 36)
  - Perloff, Jeffrey, "Approaches to Evaluating the Local Public Works Program", 1977 (Box 59)
  - Perry, George
    - "Determinants of Wage Inflation Around the World," Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1975 (Box 31)
    - "Tax Cuts and the Economic Outlook", 1978 (Box 64)
    - "What Have We Learned About Disinflation?" Brooking Panel on Economic Activity, 1983 (Box 25)
  - Phelps, Edmund S.
    - "Checking Contractual Inflation Without Causing Recession", 1977 (Box 62)
    - "Okun's Micro-Macro System: A Review Article", undated (Box 30)
  - Porter, Richard, Thomas Simpson, and Eileen Mauskopf, "Financial Innovation and the Monetary Aggregates," prepared for Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1979 (Box 58)
  - Rashish, Myer, "The International Impact of American Economic Policy", 1982 (Box 50)
  - Rees, Albert, "New Policies to Fight Inflation", 1978 (Box 64)
  - Ripley, Frank C., "Economic Policy and Growth: A Production Function Approach", 1977 (Box 35)
  - Ronk, Sally, "Current Economic and Financial Trends", 1974 (Box 31)
  - Rosen, Sherwin, "Improving the Structure of Labor Markets", 1977 (Box 2)
  - Ruggles, Richard and Nancy, "Integrated Economic accounts for the United States 1947-1980, " manuscript on United States wealth using national balance sheets, 1981 November 18 (Box 1)
  - Rutledge, John, "Statement Before the U.S. Senate Committee on the Budget", 1982 (Box 62)
  - Salant, Walter
    - Reprints, 1951-1981 (Box 47)
    - "Surveillance of Exchange Rate Policies: Comments on Papers by Giersch and Cooper", 1976 (Box 31)
    - "Theories of World Stagflation", 1976 (Box 58)
  - Sargent, Thomas J., "The Ends of Four Big Inflations," National Bureau of Economic Research study, 1980 August (Box 1)
  - Schelling, Thomas C. "Choice and Consequence", 1984 (Box 1)
  - Schioppa, Tommaso Padoa, "Rules and Institutes in the Government of Multicountry Economies", 1983 (Box 25)
  - Shimano, Takuji, "Disorder in the International Monetary System," prepared for Japan-U.S. Assembly, 1975 (Box 60)
  - Simpson, Thomas et al., "Recent Revisions in the Money Stock", circa 1981 (Box 41)
  - Sims, Christopher, "Policy Analysis with Econometric Models," prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38)
  - Sinai, Allen, "The Prospects of a Capital Shortage in the US", 1976 (Box 8)
  - Smith, James D., editor, "The Personal Distribution of Income and Wealth", 1975 (Box 2)
  - Sohmen, Egon, "Allocative Efficiency and Antitrust", 1975 (Box 31)
  - Solomon, Anthony M., "Responding to Financial Stresses", 1983 (Box 8)
  - Spann, Robert, "Tax Revenue and Economic Effects of Tax Exempt State and Local Bonds", 1975 (Box 3)
  - Spitaeller, E., "An Analysis of Inflation in the Seven Main Industrial Countries, 1958-76", 1977 (Box 59)
  - Stein, Herbert
    - "Agenda for the Study of Macroeconomic Policy", 1982 (Box 19)
    - "Expectations, Credibility, and All That", 1981 (Box 41)
    - "Fiscal Policy", undated (Box 38, 57)
    - "How to Cut Taxes", 1978 (Box 19)
    - "Interest Rate Anxieties", 1983 (Box 50)
    - "Mystery of the Declining Dollar", 1978 (Box 59)
    - "Presidents and Economists", 1981 (Box 52)
    - "Remembrance of Administrations Past", 1981 (Box 44)
    - "Suppose There Is No Recession", 1982 (Box 39)
    - "A View of Monetary Policy, 1979-1982", 1983 (Box 60)
    - "What Can Money Do?", 1983 (Box 62)
  - Summers, Lawrence
    - "Measuring Unemployment," Brookings Institution, 1981 (Box 10)
    - "Unemployment in the 1980 Recession" prepared for Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, circa 1980 (Box 60)
  - Sweeney, Richard and Thomas Willett
    - "Concepts of Efficiency and Speculation in the Foreign Exchange Market", undated (Box 61)
    - "The International Transmission of Inflation," prepared for Conference on Bank Credit, Money and Inflation in Open Economies, 1974 (Box 60)
  - Tanzi, Vito, "Inflation, Indexation, and Interest Income Taxation", 1975 (Box 59)
  - Taylor, John B.
    - "Cyclical Swings in Inflation and Output", 1980 (Box 4)
    - "The Swedish Investment Funds System as a Stabilization Policy Rule," prepared for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1982 (Box 38)
  - Terleckyj, Nestor, "R&D, Innovation and the Economy", 1983 (Box 49)
  - Theil, Henri, "The System-Wide Approach to Microeconomics," Hennipman Lecture, 1978 (Box 35)
  - Tideman, T. Nicolaus
    - "The Impact on Investment Incentives of Tax Credits, Inflation, and Inflation Adjustments", 1975 (Box 59, 66)
    - "Saving and Investment Aspects of Corporate and Personal Tax Integration," with Warrem Weber, Conference on Tax Research, Treasury Department, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Tinsely, P.A. et al., "Policy Robustness", 1982 (Box 4)
  - Tobin, James
    - "Asset Accumulation and Economic Activity: Reflections on Contemporary Macroeconomic Theory", 1978 (Box 39)
    - "Stabilization Policy Ten Years After", 1980 (Box 9)
  - Triffin, Robert
    - "How to End the World 'Infession: Paliatives or Fundamental Reforms?" Centre for European Policy Studies Conference, 1982 (Box 37)
    - "The Threat to World Economic Order," prepared for the Japan-U.S. Assembly, 1975 (Box 59)
      Includes comments
  - Tullock, Gordon, "On Inflation and the Debt", 1975 (Box 2)
  - Tumlir, Jan, "The New Protectionism: Transatlantic Similarities and Contrasts,Conference on Challenges to a Liberal International Economic Order", 1977 (Box 8)
  - Uchida, Tadao, "Threat to World Economy from Inflation and Recession," prepared for Japan-U.S. Assembly, 1980 (Box 60)
  - Vak, Karl, "Innovation and International Competitiveness, Commerce Bank, Vienna," prepared for AEI conference on Political Economy of Austria, 1981 (Box 30)
  - Vasquez, Thomas, ADR paper outline (Box 66)
  - Volker, Paul
    - "Informal Remarks to the American Enterprise Institute", 1979 (Box 39)
    - "The International Exchange Rate System", 1976 (Box 36)
    - "Statement Before the Committee on Banking, Finance and Urban Affairs", 1980 (Box 42)
    - "Statement Before Subcommittee on Domestic Monetary Policy", 1980 (Box 3)
    - "Sustainable Recovery: Setting the Stage, presentation to 58th Annual Meeting of New England Council", 1982 (Box 5)
  - Von Furstenberg, George
    - "Corporate Taxes and Financing Under Continuing Inflation", undated (Box 38, 57)
    - "Fiscal Deficits: From Business as Usual to a Breach of the Policy Rules?", 1983 (Box 25)
    - "Flow of Funds Analysis and the Economic Outlook", 1975 (Box 31)
    - "The Government and Capital Formation," with Burton Malkiel, undated (Box 58)
    - "Stabilization Characteristics of Unemployment Insurance", 1976 (Box 59)
  - Wallich, Henry C.
    - "Exchange-Market Intervention: Issues and Views", 1982 (Box 39)
    - "Foreign Exchange: New Tactics Needs?", 1980 (Box 14)
    - "From Multiplier to Quantity Theory", 1975 (Box 59)
    - "Maintaining the Strength of the International Capital Market", 1977 (Box 35)
    - "Some Uses of Ecnomics", 1982 (Box 39)
  - Weber, Arnold R., "Collective Bargaining and Wage Settlements in 1976", undated (Box 29)
  - Weidenbaum, Murray, "The Potential for Reducing Inflationary Pressures by Reforming Government Regulation", undated (Box 38)
  - Weitzman, Martin, "Negotiating Contracts for Full Employment", undated (Box 3)
  - Welch, Finish, "Minimum Wages 1977: A Misguided Idea Whose Time Has Passed" (Box 2)
  - Wenglowski, Gary "The 1977-1978 Business Outlook: Supply Inflation" (Box 2)
  - Wenninger, John and Charles Sivesind, "Changing the MI Definition", 1979 (Box 21)
  - White, James, "The Implications of Index-Linked Financial Contracts for General Economic Stability", 1975 (Box 35)
  - White, W.H., "The Anti-inflationary Advantages from Indexation of Financial Contracts", 1975 (Box 2)
  - White, William, "Improving the Demand for Money Function in Moderate Inflation, IMF", 1977 (Box 5)
  - Whitman, Marina v.N.
    - "International Interdependence and the U.S. Economy", 1976 (Box 38)
    - "The Management of U.S. Economic Relations with Other Industrialized Countries", undated (Box 62)
    - "The Viability of the International Economic Order", 1976 (Box 31)
  - Willett, Thomas D.
    - "On Applying Public Choice Analysis to the Study of International Integration," preliminary draft, 1979 (Box 67)
    - "The Eurocurrency Market, Exchange Rate Systems, and National Financial Policies", 1974 (Box 60)
  - Wingerter, Robert G., "We Can Only Have What We Produce", 1975 (Box 5)
  - Wojnilower, A. M., "The Central Role of Credit Crunches in Recent Financial History," prepared for Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1980 (Box 60)
  - Yeager, Leland B., Experiences with Stopping Inflation, manuscript, 1980 (Box 41)
  - Ypersele, Jacques van, "Operating Principles and Procedures of the European Monetary System", 1979 (Box 11)
- Index cards, undated
  Contains index cards containing contact information for individuals, such as addresses and phone numbers.
  - Contact information file, undated (Box 65)
- Sound recordings, 1977-1982
  Contains recordings of discussions on economics with Henry Aaron, Phillip D. Cagan, William Fellner, Rudolph Penner, and Herbert Stein.
  - Sound recording of the Public Policy Forums program, 27 May 1977
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 87005_a_0003733
    Dr. Henry Aaron, assistant secretary of health, education, and welfare for planning and evaluation in the Carter administration, and Dr. Rudolph Penner, resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute, discuss ways to avoid bankruptcy of the Social Security program. Aaron explains the Carter administration's solution to the problem, and then alternate solutions--increasing payroll taxes, raising the retirement age, changing the husband/wife payment system--are proposed and debated.
  - Sound recording of the Public Policy Forums program, 10 December 1982
    Use copy reference number: 87005_a_0003735
    Dr. Phillip D. Cagan, Dr. William Fellner, Dr. Rudolph Penner, and Dr. Herbert Stein discuss policies for economic recovery and growth. Regarding what should and should not be done to improve the economic situation in 1982, they consider the role of the Federal Reserve, the importance of keeping inflation down, why proposals in Congress will not successfully deal with unemployment, and raising taxes.